The job of uncovering the global food waste scandal
بدأت في العمل على كشف فضيحة مخلفات الطعام العالمية
started for me when I was 15 years old.
عندما كنت في سن الخامسة عشرة.
I bought some pigs. I was living in Sussex.
اشتريت بعض الخنازير. وكنت أعيش في ساسكس.
And I started to feed them in the most traditional
وبدأت بإطعامها بالطريقة الأكثر تقليدية
and environmentally friendly way.
والأكثر محافظة على البيئة.
I went to my school kitchen, and I said,
ذهبت إلى مطعم مدرستي، وقلت،
"Give me the scraps that my school friends have turned
"أعطني بقايا الطعام التي ترّفع عنها أصدقائي
their noses up at."
في المدرسة."
I went to the local baker and took their stale bread.
ذهبت إلى المخبز المحلي وأخذت خبزهم العفن.
I went to the local greengrocer, and I went to a farmer
ذهبت إلى بائع الخضار، وذهبت إلى مُزارع
who was throwing away potatoes because they were
كان يتخلص من البطاطس لأنها لا تطابق
the wrong shape or size for supermarkets.
الشكل والحجم المطلوب في الأسواق المركزية.
This was great. My pigs turned that food waste
كان ذلك رائعاً. خنازيري حوّلت فضلات الطعام تلك
into delicious pork. I sold that pork
إلى لحم خنزير لذيذ. بعت لحم الخنزير ذلك
to my school friends' parents, and I made
إلى آباء أصدقائي في المدرسة، و قد كوّنت
a good pocket money addition to my teenage allowance.
مصروف جيب جيد بالإضافة إلى مصروفي أيام المراهقة.
But I noticed that most of the food that I was giving my pigs
لكني لاحظت أن معظم الطعام الذي أطعمه لخنازيري
was in fact fit for human consumption,
كان للاستهلاك البشري في الواقع،
and that I was only scratching the surface,
وأنني كنت أتعامل مع المشكلة بسطحية،
and that right the way up the food supply chain,
وهذا ما تفعله سلسلة الإمدادات الغذائية،
in supermarkets, greengrocers, bakers, in our homes,
في الأسواق المركزية، ومحلات الخضار، والمخابز، وفي بيوتنا،
in factories and farms, we were hemorrhaging out food.
في المصانع والمزارع، كنا نبدد الطعام.
Supermarkets didn't even want to talk to me
الأسواق المركزية لم ترغب أن تتحدث معي حتى
about how much food they were wasting.
عن مقدار ما كانوا يبددونه من الطعام.
I'd been round the back. I'd seen bins full of food
كنت أتجول في الخلف. وقد رأيت صناديق ممتلئة بالطعام
being locked and then trucked off to landfill sites,
تم غلقها ومن ثم نقلها بالشاحنات إلى مواقع مكب النفايات،
and I thought, surely there is something more sensible
وفكرت، بالتأكيد هناك شيء معقول
to do with food than waste it.
نفعله بالطعام أكثر من تبديده.
One morning, when I was feeding my pigs,
في صباح يومٍ ما، عندما كنت أطعم خنازيري،
I noticed a particularly tasty-looking sun-dried tomato loaf
لاحظت كتلة طماطم ذات منظر شهي مجفف تحت الشمس
that used to crop up from time to time.
يُزرع بالعادة من وقت لآخر.
I grabbed hold of it,
أخذت قبضة منها،
sat down, and ate my breakfast with my pigs. (Laughter)
جلست، ثم تناولت فطوري مع خنازيري. (ضحك)
That was the first act of what I later learned to call freeganism,
كان ذلك هو الفعل الأول لما تعلمت لاحقاً أن أسميه بـ تناول الطعام المبدد،
really an exhibition of the injustice of food waste,
كان يعرض حقاً الممارسة الظالمة تجاه مخلفات الطعام،
and the provision of the solution to food waste,
و توفير الحلول لمشكلة مخلفات الطعام،
which is simply to sit down and eat food,
وهي ببساطة الجلوس وتناول الطعام،
rather than throwing it away.
بدلاً من التخلص منه.
That became, as it were, a way of confronting
أصبح ذلك، كما كان، وسيلة لمواجهة
large businesses in the business of wasting food,
المشاريع الكبيرة المتعلقة بتبديد الطعام،
and exposing, most importantly, to the public,
والأهم من هذا، لنكشف للعامة
that when we're talking about food being thrown away,
أنه عنما نتحدث عن الطعام الذي يُرمى،
we're not talking about rotten stuff, we're not talking about
فإننا لا نتحدث عن الطعام المتعفّن، ولا نتحدث عن
stuff that's beyond the pale.
الطعام الغير مقبول.
We're talking about good, fresh food that is being wasted
نحن نتحدث عن طعام جيد و طازج يتعرض للتبديد
on a colossal scale.
على نحو مروّع.
Eventually, I set about writing my book,
في النهاية، قررت أن أكتب كتابي،
really to demonstrate the extent of this problem
للتدليل على حجم هذه المشكلة
on a global scale. What this shows is
على نطاق عالمي. ما يوضحه هذا هو
a nation-by-nation breakdown of the likely level
هبوط المستوى المحتمل لمخلفات الطعام
of food waste in each country in the world.
في كل دولة من دول العالم.
Unfortunately, empirical data, good, hard stats, don't exist,
لسوء الحظ، لا توجد بيانات تجريبية وإحصائيات جيدة وثابتة،
and therefore to prove my point, I first of all had to find
وبالتالي، لكي أثبت وجهة نظري، علي أولاً أن أجد
some proxy way of uncovering
طريقة معتمدة للكشف
how much food was being wasted.
عن كمية الطعام المبدد.
So I took the food supply of every single country
لذا، أخذت الإمدادات الغذائية لكل بلد
and I compared it to what was actually likely
وقارنتها بما كان من المحتمل
to be being consumed in each country.
استهلاكه في كل دولة.
That's based on diet intake surveys, it's based on
يعتمد ذلك على دراسات حول اتباع الأنظمة الغذائية، و يعتمد على
levels of obesity, it's based on a range of factors
مستويات البدانة، و يعتمد على مجموعة من العوامل
that gives you an approximate guess
التي تعطي تخمينا تقريبيا
as to how much food is actually going into people's mouths.
لكمية الطعام الذي يتناوله الناس بالفعل، على سبيل المثال.
That black line in the middle of that table
الخط الأسود في منتصف ذلك الجدول
is the likely level of consumption
هو المستوى المحتمل للاستهلاك
with an allowance for certain levels of inevitable waste.
مع تفاوت لمستويات محددة للمخلفات التي لا يمكن اجتنابها.
There will always be waste. I'm not that unrealistic
سيكون هناك مخلفات دائماً. أنا لست ذلك الشخص الغير واقعي
that I think we can live in a waste-free world.
الذي يظن أننا يمكن أن نعيش في عالم خال من الفضلات.
But that black line shows what a food supply should be
لكن ذلك الخط الأسود يبين كمية الإمداد الغذائي اللازم
in a country if they allow for a good, stable, secure,
لدولةٍ ما إذا سمحوا بنظام غذائي جيد، و ثابت، و آمن
nutritional diet for every person in that country.
لكل شخص في تلك الدولة.
Any dot above that line, and you'll quickly notice that
أي نقطة تقع فوق ذلك الخط، وستلاحظون بسرعة أن
that includes most countries in the world,
ذلك يشمل معظم دول العالم،
represents unnecessary surplus, and is likely to reflect
تمثل الفائض الغير لازم، ويُرجح أن تعكس
levels of waste in each country.
مستويات المخلفات في كل دولة.
As a country gets richer, it invests more and more
عندما تصبح الدولة أكثر ثراءً، تستثمر أكثر فأكثر
in getting more and more surplus
في الحصول على المزيد والمزيد من الفائض
into its shops and restaurants,
في محلاتها ومطاعمها،
and as you can see, most European
وكما ترون، أغلب الدول
and North American countries
الأوروبية ودول أمريكا الشمالية
fall between 150 and 200 percent
تقع بين 150 و 200 بالمئة
of the nutritional requirements of their populations.
من الاحتياجات الغذائية لسكانها.
So a country like America has twice as much food
فدولة مثل أمريكا لديها كمية طعام
on its shop shelves and in its restaurants
على رفوف متاجرها وفي مطاعمها
than is actually required to feed the American people.
تبلغ ضعفيّ ما هو مطلوب بالفعل لإطعام الشعب الأمريكي.
But the thing that really struck me,
لكن الشيء الذي أدهشني فعلاً،
when I plotted all this data, and it was a lot of numbers,
عندما فرزت كل هذه البيانات، وكانت عبارة عن كثير من الأرقام،
was that you can see how it levels off.
كان أنه بإمكانكم أن تروا كيف تستقر هذه الأرقام.
Countries rapidly shoot towards that 150 mark,
الدول تنطلق بسرعة باتجاه علامة 150 تلك،
and then they level off, and they don't really go on rising
ثم تستقر، ولا تستمر في الواقع بالصعود
as you might expect.
كما تتوقعون.
So I decided to unpack that data a little bit further
لذا قررت أن أفك تلك البيانات أكثر قليلاً
to see if that was true or false.
لأرى إن كان ذلك صحيحاً أم لا.
And that's what I came up with.
وهذا ما توصلت إليه.
If you include not just the food that ends up
إذا لم تشملوا فقط الطعام الذي ينتهي
in shops and restaurants, but also the food
في المحلات التجارية و المطاعم، بل أيضاً الطعام
that people feed to livestock,
الذي يطعمه الناس للماشية،
the maize, the soy, the wheat, that humans could eat
الذرة، و فول الصويا، و القمح، الذي يمكن أن يتناوله البشر
but choose to fatten livestock instead to produce
لكنهم بدلاً من ذلك اختاروا تغذية الماشية به لإنتاج
increasing amounts of meat and dairy products,
كميات متزايدة من اللحم والمنتجات اليومية،
what you find is that most rich countries
ستجدون أن أكثر الدول ثراءً
have between three and four times the amount of food
تملك ما بين ثلاثة إلى أربعة أضعاف الطعام
that their population needs to feed itself.
الذي يحتاجه سكانها لإطعام أنفسهم.
A country like America has four times the amount of food
دولة مثل أمريكا تملك أربعة أضعاف كمية الطعام
that it needs.
الذي تحتاجه.
When people talk about the need to increase global
عندما يتحدث الناس عن الحاجة لزيادة الإنتاج
food production to feed those nine billion people
العالمي للطعام لإطعام التسعة مليار شخص
that are expected on the planet by 2050,
المتوقع وجودهم بحلول عام 2050،
I always think of these graphs.
دائماً أفكر بتلك الرسوم البيانية.
The fact is, we have an enormous buffer
الحقيقة هي، أنه لدينا في الدول الغنية
in rich countries between ourselves and hunger.
حاجز هائل بيننا وبين الجوع.
We've never had such gargantuan surpluses before.
لم يكن لدينا مثل هذه الفوائض الهائلة من قبل.
In many ways, this is a great success story
في عدة نواحي، هذه قصة نجاح عظيمة
of human civilization, of the agricultural surpluses
للحضارة الإنسانية، للفوائض الزراعية
that we set out to achieve 12,000 years ago.
التي خططنا للوصول إليها منذ 12,000 سنة ماضية.
It is a success story. It has been a success story.
إنها قصة نجاح. لقد كانت قصة نجاح.
But what we have to recognize now is that we are
لكن ما يجب أن ندركه الآن هو أننا
reaching the ecological limits that our planet can bear,
نصل إلى الحدود البيئية التي يتحملها كوكبنا
and when we chop down forests, as we are every day,
وعندما نقطع الغابات، كما نفعل كل يوم،
to grow more and more food,
لزراعة المزيد والمزيد من المحاصيل الغذائية،
when we extract water from depleting water reserves,
عندما نستخرج الماء من احتياطات الماء المستنزفة،
when we emit fossil fuel emissions in the quest
عندما ننشر ابنعاثات الوقود المتحجر في سبيل
to grow more and more food,
زراعة المزيد والمزيد من المحاصيل الغذائية،
and then we throw away so much of it,
ومن ثم نتخلص من الكثير منها،
we have to think about what we can start saving.
علينا أن نفكر في ما يمكن أن ندخره أولاً.
And yesterday, I went to one of the local supermarkets
البارحة، ذهبت إلى أحد المراكز التجارية المحلية
that I often visit to
التي أزورها غالباً
inspect, if you like, what they're throwing away.
لأفتش، إن شئتم، عن الأشياء التي يتخلصون منها.
I found quite a few packets of biscuits amongst
وجدت علب بسكويت قليلة جداً وسط
all the fruit and vegetables and everything else
الخضروات والفواكه وكل شيء آخر
that was in there.
موجود هناك.
And I thought, well this could serve as a symbol for today.
وفكرت، أن ذلك يمكن أن يفيد كمثال لليوم.
So I want you to imagine that these nine biscuits
لذلك أريدكم أن تتخيلوا أن هذه التسع قطع من البسكويت
that I found in the bin represent the global food supply,
التي وجدتها في الحاوية تمثل الإمدادات الغذائية العالمية،
okay? We start out with nine.
حسناً؟ بدأنا بتسعة.
That's what's in fields around the world every single year.
هذا ما يوجد في الحقول حول العالم كل عام.
The first biscuit we're going to lose
قطعة البسكويت الأولى التي سنفقدها
before we even leave the farm.
قبل حتى أن نغادر المزرعة.
That's a problem primarily associated with
هذه مشكلة ترتبط بشكل أساسي
developing work agriculture, whether it's
بالزراعة في العالم النامي، سواء كانت
a lack of infrastructure, refrigeration, pasteurization,
افتقارا للبنية التحتية، أو التبريد، أو التعقيم،
grain stores, even basic fruit crates, which means
مخازن الحبوب، أو حتى صناديق الفواكه الأساسية، ما يعني
that food goes to waste before it even leaves the fields.
أن الغذاء يذهب للنفايات حتى قبل أن يخرج من الحقول.
The next three biscuits are the foods that we decide
قطع البسكويت الثلاثة الموالية تمثل الطعام الذي نقرر
to feed to livestock, the maize, the wheat and the soya.
إطعامه للماشية، الذرة، والقمح، وفول الصويا.
Unfortunately, our beasts are inefficient animals,
لسوء الحظ، بهائمنا حيوانات غير فعالة،
and they turn two-thirds of that into feces and heat,
وهي تحول ثلثي الطعام إلى براز ونار،
so we've lost those two, and we've only kept this one
إذن فقدنا هاتين القطعتين، واحتفظنا بهذه فقط
in meat and dairy products.
في اللحم والمنتجات اليومية.
Two more we're going to throw away directly into bins.
وقطعتين اُخرتين سوف نرميهما مباشرة في الحاويات.
This is what most of us think of when we think
هذا ما يفكر به معظمنا عندما نفكر
of food waste, what ends up in the garbage,
في بقايا الطعام، التي ينتهي أمرها في القمامة،
what ends up in supermarket bins,
التي ينتهي أمرها في حاويات المراكز التجارية،
what ends up in restaurant bins. We've lost another two,
وفي حاويات المطاعم. لقد فقدنا قطعتين أٌخرتين،
and we've left ourselves with just four biscuits to feed on.
وأبقينا لأنفسنا أربعة قطع فقط من البسكويت للتزود بالغذاء.
That is not a superlatively efficient use of global resources,
هذا لا يُعد استخداما اقتصاديا مفرطا للموارد العالمية،
especially when you think of the billion hungry people
خاصة عندما نفكر في مليار الجوعى من الناس
that exist already in the world.
الموجودين بالفعل في العالم.
Having gone through the data, I then needed
بعد أن فحصت البيانات جيداً، احتجت عندها
to demonstrate where that food ends up.
لإثبات ماذا يحل بالطعام.
Where does it end up? We're used to seeing the stuff
ماذا يحل به في نهاية الأمر؟ اعتدنا على رؤية الطعام
on our plates, but what about all the stuff
على صحوننا، لكن ماذا عن كل الطعام
that goes missing in between?
الذي يُفقد في الوسط؟
Supermarkets are an easy place to start.
المراكز التجارية مكان سهل لنبدأ به.
This is the result of my hobby,
هذه هي النتيجة من وراء هوايتي،
which is unofficial bin inspections. (Laughter)
وهي التفتيش عن الحاويات غير الرسمية. (ضحك)
Strange you might think, but if we could rely on corporations
قد يبدو لكم أنه غريب، لكن إن نستطيع الاعتماد على الشركات
to tell us what they were doing in the back of their stores,
لتخبرنا ماذا كانوا يفعلون خلف متاجرهم،
we wouldn't need to go sneaking around the back,
لن نحتاج للتسلل للخلف،
opening up bins and having a look at what's inside.
ولفتح الحاويات واكتشاف ما بداخلها.
But this is what you can see more or less on
لكن هذا ما يمكن أن تروه إلى حدٍ ما
every street corner in Britain, in Europe, in North America.
في كل زاوية شارع في بريطانيا وأوروبا وأمريكا الشمالية.
It represents a colossal waste of food,
إنها تمثل بقايا هائلة من الطعام،
but what I discovered whilst I was writing my book
لكن ما اكتشفته بينما كنت أكتب كتابي
was that this very evident abundance of waste
كان أن هذه الكثرة الواضحة من بقايا الطعام
was actually the tip of the iceberg.
كانت في الواقع البداية فقط.
When you start going up the supply chain,
عندما تبدؤون في بناء سلسلة الإمداد،
you find where the real food waste is happening
تجدون ما يحدث لبقايا الطعام الحقيقية
on a gargantuan scale.
على نحو هائل.
Can I have a show of hands
هلاّ رفعتكم أيديكم
if you have a loaf of sliced bread in your house?
إن كان لديكم شرائح من رغيف الخبز في منازلكم؟
Who lives in a household where that crust --
من يسكن في منزل حيث تلك القشرة --
that slice at the first and last end of each loaf --
تلك الشريحة في الطرف الأول والأخير من كل رغيف --
who lives in a household where it does get eaten?
من يسكن في منزل تؤكل فيه هذه القشرة؟
Okay, most people, not everyone, but most people,
حسناً، معظم الناس، ليس الجميع، لكن أغلب الناس
and this is, I'm glad to say, what I see across the world,
وهذا ما رأيته حول العالم، و يسعدني قول ذلك،
and yet has anyone seen a supermarket or sandwich shop
ومع ذلك هل رأى منكم من قبل محل تجاري أو محل شطائر
anywhere in the world that serves sandwiches
في أي مكان في العالم يقدم الشطائر
with crusts on it? (Laughter)
بالقشرة فوقها؟ (ضحك)
I certainly haven't.
أنا متأكد أني لم أره من قبل.
So I kept on thinking, where do those crusts go? (Laughter)
لذا واصلت التفكير، أين تذهب هذه الطبقات؟ (ضحك)
This is the answer, unfortunately:
هذا هو الجواب، للأسف:
13,000 slices of fresh bread coming out of
13.000 شريحة من الخبز الطازج تخرج من
this one single factory every single day, day-fresh bread.
هذا المصنع كل يوم، خبز طازج يومياً.
In the same year that I visited this factory,
في نفس السنة التي زرت فيها المطعم،
I went to Pakistan, where people in 2008 were going hungry
ذهبت إلى باكستان، حيث عاش الناس في مجاعة عام 2008
as a result of a squeeze on global food supplies.
بسبب أزمة إمدادات الغذاء العالمية.
We contribute to that squeeze
ساهمنا في تلك الأزمة
by depositing food in bins here in Britain
من خلال إيداع الطعام في الحاويات هنا في بريطانيا
and elsewhere in the world. We take food
وفي كل مكان في العالم. نحن ننزع الطعام
off the market shelves that hungry people depend on.
الذي يعتمد عليه الجوعى من على رفوف المتاجر.
Go one step up, and you get to farmers,
اصعدوا خطوة واحدة، و ستصلون للمزارعين،
who throw away sometimes a third or even more
الذين يتخلصون من ثلث وأكثر
of their harvest because of cosmetic standards.
من حصادهم بسبب المعايير الجمالية.
This farmer, for example, has invested 16,000 pounds
هذا المُزارع، على سبيل المثال، استثمر 16.000 باوند
in growing spinach, not one leaf of which he harvested,
في زراعة السبانخ، لم يحصد ورقة منها
because there was a little bit of grass growing in amongst it.
بسبب وجود القليل من العشب النابت بينها.
Potatoes that are cosmetically imperfect,
البطاطا الناقصة جمالياً
all going for pigs.
تذهب جميعها للخنازير.
Parsnips that are too small for supermarket specifications,
الجزر الأبيض الصغير جداً بالنسبة لمواصفات المحال التجارية،
tomatoes in Tenerife,
الطماطم في تينيريف،
oranges in Florida,
البرتقال في فلوريدا،
bananas in Ecuador, where I visited last year,
الموز في الإكوادور، التي زرتها العالم الماضي،
all being discarded. This is one day's waste
كلها تم التخلص منها. هذه نفايات يوم واحد
from one banana plantation in Ecuador.
من مزرعة موز واحدة في الإكوادور.
All being discarded, perfectly edible,
كلها تم التخلص منها، وهي صالحة للأكل،
because they're the wrong shape or size.
لأنها لا تطابق الحجم أو الشكل المطلوب.
If we do that to fruit and vegetables,
إذا فعلنا ذلك بالفواكه و الخضروات،
you bet we can do it to animals too.
أراهن أننا سنفعله أيضاُ مع الحيوانات.
Liver, lungs, heads, tails,
الكبد، الكليتان، الرؤوس، الأذيال،
kidneys, testicles,
الرئتان، الأعضاء،
all of these things which are traditional,
كل هذه الأشياء أجزاء
delicious and nutritious parts of our gastronomy
تقليدية لذيذة ومغذية من أكلنا
go to waste. Offal consumption has halved
تذهب للنفاية. استهلاك المخلفات انخفض إلى النصف
in Britain and America in the last 30 years.
في بريطانيا وأمريكا في الثلاثين عاماً الماضية.
As a result, this stuff gets fed to dogs at best,
نتيجة لذلك، هذه المخلفات تُعطى للكلاب في أفضل الأحوال،
or is incinerated.
أو تُحرق.
This man, in Kashgar, Xinjiang province, in Western China,
هذا الرجل، في كاشقار، في مقاطعة زينقيانغ جنوب الصين
is serving up his national dish.
يقدم طبقه الشعبي.
It's called sheep's organs.
يسمّى أعضاء الخروف.
It's delicious, it's nutritious,
إنه لذيذ و مغذي،
and as I learned when I went to Kashgar,
وكما علمت عندما ذهبت إلى كاشقار،
it symbolizes their taboo against food waste.
أنه يرمز إلى تحريمهم لتبديد الطعام.
I was sitting in a roadside cafe.
كنت أجلس في مقهى على جانب الطريق.
A chef came to talk to me, I finished my bowl,
أتى طباخ ليتحدث إلي، أنهيت طبقي،
and halfway through the conversation, he stopped talking
وفي منتصف حديثنا، توقف عن الكلام
and he started frowning into my bowl.
وبدأ ينظر عابساً إلى طبقي.
I thought, "My goodness, what taboo have I broken?
فكرت، "يا إلهي، ماذا تجاوزت من محرمات؟
How have I insulted my host?"
كيف أهنت مضيفي؟"
He pointed at three grains of rice
أشار إلى ثلاث حبات من الأرز
at the bottom of my bowl, and he said, "Clean." (Laughter)
في قعر طبقي، وقال: " نظف!" (ضحك)
I thought, "My God, you know, I go around the world
فكرت، "يا إلهى، أنت تعلمون، أجوب العالم
telling people to stop wasting food.
لأدعو الناس للتوقف عن إهدار الطعام.
This guy has thrashed me at my own game." (Laughter)
وهذا الرجل سحقني في لعبتي." (ضحك)
But it gave me faith. It gave me faith that we, the people,
لكنه أعطاني إيماناً. جعلني أؤمن أننا نحن، الناس،
do have the power to stop this tragic waste of resources
نملك القوة لإيقاف هذا الإهدار المأساوي لموارد الغذاء
if we regard it as socially unacceptable
إذا نظرنا إليه كعمل غير مقبول اجتماعياً
to waste food on a colossal scale,
أن نهدر الطعام على نطاق واسع،
if we make noise about it, tell corporations about it,
لو أحدثنا ضجة حول ذلك، و نبهنا الشركات
tell governments we want to see an end to food waste,
وأخبرنا الحكومات أننا نريد أن نرى نهاية لتبديد الطعام.
we do have the power to bring about that change.
نحن نملك القوة لإحداث ذلك التغيير.
Fish, 40 to 60 percent of European fish
السمك، 40 إلى 60 % من سمك أوروبا
are discarded at sea, they don't even get landed.
يتم التخلص منه في البحر، حتى أنه لا يؤخذ إلى اليابسة.
In our homes, we've lost touch with food.
في بيوتنا، لم نعد نتعامل جيداً مع طعامنا.
This is an experiment I did on three lettuces.
هذه تجربة قمت بتجربتها على ثلاث خسات.
Who keeps lettuces in their fridge?
من يحفظ الخس في الثلاجة؟
Most people. The one on the left
معظم الناس. الخس على اليسار
was kept in a fridge for 10 days.
تم حفظه في الثلاجة لعشرة أيام.
The one in the middle, on my kitchen table. Not much difference.
و الخس في المنتصف، على طاولة مطبخي. لا يختلف كثيراً.
The one on the right I treated like cut flowers.
و الخس على اليمين عاملته مثل الزهور.
It's a living organism, cut the slice off,
إنها كائن حي، أزلت الشريحة،
stuck it in a vase of water,
ثبّتها في إناء من الماء،
it was all right for another two weeks after this.
وظلت بعد ذلك في حالة جيدة لأسبوعين أكثر.
Some food waste, as I said at the beginning,
بعض مخلفات الطعام، كما قلت في البداية،
will inevitably arise, so the question is,
ستظهرحتماً، لذا فالسؤال هو،
what is the best thing to do with it?
ما أفضل ما يمكننا فعله بها؟
I answered that question when I was 15.
أجبت على ذلك السؤال عندما كنت في الخامسة عشرة.
In fact, humans answered that question 6,000 years ago:
في الواقع، أجاب البشر على هذا السؤال منذ 6.000 سنة:
We domesticated pigs
قمنا بتدجين الخنازير
to turn food waste back into food.
لتحويل مخلفات الطعام مرة أخرى إلى طعام.
And yet, in Europe, that practice has become illegal
ومع ذلك، في أوروبا، هذا الفعل أصبح غير قانونيا
since 2001 as a result of the foot-and-mouth outbreak.
منذ عام 2001
It's unscientific. It's unnecessary.
إنه غير علمي. إنه غير ضروري.
If you cook food for pigs, just as if
إذا طبخنا الطعام للخنازير، تماماً مثلما
you cook food for humans, it is rendered safe.
نطبخ الطعام للبشر، فإن هذا يُصبح آمناً.
It's also a massive saving of resources.
إنه أيضاً توفير هائل للموارد.
At the moment, Europe depends on importing
تعتمد أوروبا الآن على استيراد
millions of tons of soy from South America,
ملايين الأطنان من فول الصويا من جنوب أفريقيا،
where its production contributes to global warming,
حيث يساهم إنتاجه في ظاهرة الانحباس الحراري،
to deforestation, to biodiversity loss,
وفي إزالة الغابات، وفقدان التنوع البيولوجي،
to feed livestock here in Europe.
من أجل إطعام الماشية هنا في أوروبا.
At the same time we throw away millions of tons
في ذات الوقت نحن نرمي ملايين الأطنان
of food waste which we could and should be feeding them.
من مخلفات الطعام التي يمكننا أن نطعمها الماشية ولابد لنا أن نفعل.
If we did that, and fed it to pigs, we would save
لو فعلنا ذلك، وأطعمنا الخنازير بها، سنتمكن من توفير
that amount of carbon.
هذه الكمية من الكربون.
If we feed our food waste which is the current
لو خصصنا مخلفات طعامنا وهي الطريقة الحالية
government favorite way of getting rid of food waste,
المفضلة لدى الحكومة للتخلص من مخلفات الطعام،
to anaerobic digestion, which turns food waste
للهضم اللاهوائي، الذي يحول مخلفات الطعام
into gas to produce electricity,
إلى غاز لإنتاج الكهرباء،
you save a paltry 448 kilograms of carbon dioxide
سنوفر 448 كيلو غرام من ثاني أكسيد الكربون
per ton of food waste. It's much better to feed it to pigs.
لكل طن من مخلفات الطعام. إن هذا أفضل بكثير من اطعامها للخنازير.
We knew that during the war. (Laughter)
عرفنا ذلك خلال الحرب. (ضحك)
A silver lining: It has kicked off globally,
مظهر إيجابي: إنطلق على الصعيد العالمي،
the quest to tackle food waste.
هدفه معالجة المخلفات الغذائية.
Feeding the 5,000 is an event I first organized in 2009.
إطعام 5.000 شخص هو حدث نظمته أول مرة عام 2009.
We fed 5,000 people all on food that otherwise
أطعمنا 5.000 شخص معتمدين على طعام كان
would have been wasted.
سيُبدد بصورة مختلفة لولا ذلك.
Since then, it's happened again in London,
منذ ذلك الحين، تكرر هذا الحدث في لندن مرة أخرى،
it's happening internationally, and across the country.
إنه يحدث بصورة عالمية، و عبر البلاد.
It's a way of organizations coming together
إنها وسيلة للمنظمات من أجل أن تجتمع معاً
to celebrate food, to say the best thing to do with food
لتقدّر الطعام، لتقول أن أفضل ما يمكن فعله بالطعام
is to eat and enjoy it, and to stop wasting it.
هو تناوله والاستمتاع به، والتوقف عن تبديده.
For the sake of the planet we live on,
من أجل الكوكب الذي نعيش عليه،
for the sake of our children,
من أجل أطفالنا،
for the sake of all the other
من أجل كل الكائنات الأخرى
organisms that share our planet with us,
التي تشاركنا العيش على هذا الكوكب،
we are a terrestrial animal, and we depend on our land
نحن حيوانات برية، ونحن نعتمد على أرضنا
for food. At the moment, we are trashing our land
للحصول على الغذاء. في هذا الوقت، نحن نفسد أرضنا
to grow food that no one eats.
لزراعة غذاء لا يأكله أحد.
Stop wasting food. Thank you very much. (Applause)
توقفوا عن تبديد الطعام. شكراً جزيلاً لكم. (تصفيق)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)